<chapter id="networking-commands">
   <title>Networking Commands</title>

<para>
Networking allows MSWLogo to communicate with the rest of the world.
There are numerous forms of networking and MSWLogo uses just one form.
This form is known as TCP/IP sockets (this is primarily what is used to build the Internet).
MSWLogo can receive data from other computers or send data to other computers.
The other computer does not need to be running MSWLogo although it will be likely.
When you wish MSWLogo to initiate a connection use the NETCONNECTxxx commands.
When you wish MSWLogo to accept a connect use NETACCEPTxxx commands.
You can send and receive data on either type of connection.
You can at most have 2 connections, one you initiated and one you accepted.
</para>

<para>
TCP/IP networks can run over a wide variety of devices even modems (PPP), LapLink cables etc.
CompuServe, Microsoft Network, America Online and private Internet Service Providers (ISPs) all offer TCP/IP access to the rest of the world.
What this means is that your friend can be in England and you can be in Canada and both run MSWLogo and draw on each other's screen or build games that you can both participate in.
Assuming you can find one another.
</para>

<section id="networking-tools">
  <title>Networking Tools (Outside of MSWLogo)</title>

<para>
In order to use networking within MSWLogo, it is helpful to understand the networking tools that the rest of the world uses.
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>DNS (Domain Name Service)</title>
<para>
DNS is an integral part of using TCP/IP protocols.
TCP/IP in itself only understands IP addresses that look something like 21.100.200.5 (note each number field must be less than 255).
These numbers have no intrinsic meaning and are hard for people remember, so machines are usually given names, too.
DNS is basically a bunch of machines that maintain databases that map these easy-to-remember names to IP addresses.
DNS machines talk to each other to share information.
MSWLogo uses DNS names when trying to make a connection.
DNS is not required to setup a small TCP/IP network (keep reading).
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>PING</title>
<para>
Ping is a simple command that is used to test network connectivity.
It is usually a command line program.
Most TCP/IP implementations include a PING program.
To use it just enter "PING remotenode" where remote node is the machine you'd like to test connectivity to.
PING will tell if it can reach that machine and how long it takes to reach the machine.
Until PING works don't bother trying any other TCP/IP based software (including MSWLogo Network commands).
PING will accept both forms of the address (the IP address or the name).
If the PING fails with the name then try the number (if you know it).
If the IP address works but the domain name does not it, it usually indicates a DNS problem.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>HOSTS files</title>
<para>
If there is no DNS server, you can use what is known as a <filename>HOSTS</filename> file (usually kept in <filename>C:\Windows\HOSTS</filename>).
Microsoft frequently installs a sample <filename>HOSTS</filename> file named <filename>HOSTS.SAM</filename> (copy <filename>HOSTS.SAM</filename> to <filename>HOSTS</filename> and edit it).
The <filename>HOSTS</filename> file is simply a database for mapping domain names to IP addresses.
If using a <filename>HOSTS</filename> file, then each machine on the network should use a copy of the same <filename>HOSTS</filename> file with the name to mapping of all the machines in the network.
You can have both DNS and a <filename>HOSTS</filename> file, usually the <filename>HOSTS</filename> file is checked before DNS is attempted.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara>
<title>Sockets and Services</title>
<para>
Services is to Sockets as DNS is to Network Addresses.
Services map "Service Names" like (TELNET, FTP, POPMAIL) to Socket port numbers.
You may find a SERVICES file in <filename>C:\Windows\SERVICES</filename> and you can browse it if you like.
MSWLogo does not support the Service name to Socket port number it only uses Socket port numbers.
But if you wish to connect to a service such as TELNET or act as a TELNET server then just look it up in the services file.
In general, socket numbers under 1024 are reserved for well-known services like TELNET and FTP.
It is better to use socket numbers greater than 1024 for services that you write.
</para>
</formalpara>


<formalpara>
<title>Networks</title>
<para>
If you are on a private network that is under your total control, then you can do what ever you want.
If you are on a network with other Windows PCs then you'll probably have to do without a DNS server (and use <filename>HOSTS</filename> files).
If you are part of a larger network you should contact your network administrators.
</para>
</formalpara>


<formalpara>
<title>Service Providers</title>
<para>
Some service providers do not give you a name and assign your IP address "on-the-fly".
Some service providers completely "wrap" your network access up into one application that gives all the services you need.
When asking a service providers for help tell them that you want to run a third-party application like Firefox (a Web browser).
If Firefox works, then MSWLogo should also work (for outgoing connections, anyway).
Allowing you to receive data is more complex because the other application needs to be able to find you by name or at least by a number address if they use a <filename>HOSTS</filename> file.
You can determine your IP address with a command-line tool called "ipconfig".
</para>
</formalpara>

</section>

   &command-netstartup;
   &command-netshutdown;
   &command-netaccepton;
   &command-netacceptoff;
   &command-netacceptreceivevalue;
   &command-netacceptsendvalue;
   &command-netconnecton;
   &command-netconnectoff;
   &command-netconnectsendvalue;
   &command-netconnectreceivevalue;

</chapter>
