<chapter>
   <title>Workspace Management</title>

   <section>
       <title>Procedure Definition</title>

       &command-to;
       &command-end;
       &command-define;
       &command-text;
       &command-fulltext;
       &command-copydef;
    </section>

   <section>
       <title>Variable Definition</title>

       &command-make;
       &command-name;
       &command-local;
       &command-localmake;
       &command-thing;
    </section>


   <section>
       <title>Property Lists</title>

<para>
Property lists provide a way to associate words with things.
Property lists are sometimes called "dictionaries", "associative arrays", or simply "name-value pairs".
</para>


<para>
Property lists, abbreviated "plists", are always accessed by their name--you can't get at the plist directly.
Among other things, this means you cannot pass a plist into a Logo procedure, you can only pass its name.
</para>

<para>
You can get, set, and remove properties (name-value pairs) from a plist.
If you try to get a property that doesn't exist, or you try to get a property from a plist that doesn't exist, you will get the empty list.
In general, you shouldn't care if a property list exists or not.
However, if you do care, you can use <link linkend="command-plist">PLISTS</link> to get the names of all unburied property lists.
</para>

<para>
Names of property lists are always case-insensitive.
Names of individual properties are case-sensitive or case-insensitive depending on the value of <link linkend="command-caseignorep">CASEIGNOREDP</link>, which is TRUE by default.
</para>

       &command-pprop;
       &command-gprop;
       &command-remprop;
       &command-plist;
    </section>

   <section>
       <title>Workspace Predicates</title>

       &command-procedurep;
       &command-primitivep;
       &command-definedp;
       &command-namep;
       &command-macrop;
    </section>

   <section>
       <title>Workspace Queries</title>

<para>
Most workspace query procedures output a "contents list", which can be used as input to the <link linkend="workspace-inspection">Workspace Inspection</link> procedures.
All procedures whose input is indicated as "contentslist" will accept any of the following:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>A single word (taken as a procedure name)</listitem>
<listitem>A list of words (taken as procedure names)</listitem>
<listitem>A list of two lists (taken as procedure names and variable names, respectivly)</listitem>
<listitem>A list of three lists (taken as procedure names, variable names, and property list names, respectivly)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

       &command-contents;
       &command-buried;
       &command-procedures;
       &command-names;
       &command-plists;
       &command-namelist;
       &command-pllist;
    </section>

</chapter>
