<section id="command-ellipsearc2">
<title>ELLIPSEARC2</title>
<indexterm><primary>ELLIPSEARC2</primary></indexterm>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term>Synopsis</term>
<listitem>
<synopsis><command>ELLIPSEARC2</command> <parameter>angle</parameter> <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> <parameter>startangle</parameter></synopsis>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Description</term>
<listitem>
<para>
ELLIPSEARC2 Moves the turtle clockwise over an elliptic arc. This arc will span <parameter>angle</parameter> degrees, starting at <parameter>startangle</parameter> degrees
and ending at (<parameter>startangle</parameter> + <parameter>angle</parameter>) degrees.
</para>

<para>
The size of the ellipse is based on the <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> and <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> inputs.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Drawing details</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The <parameter>crosswise.semiaxis</parameter> input is the distance from the center-point of the ellipse to the ellipse's edge along the crosswise axis.
The <parameter>inline.semiaxis</parameter> input is the distance from the center-point of the ellipse to the ellipse's edge along the inline axis.
</para>

<para>
The actual orientation of the ellipse's axes relative to the turtle direction will depend on the chosen <parameter>startangle</parameter>.
</para>

<para>
The inline axis will start at 0 degrees and will end at 180 degrees; the crosswise axis will start at 90 degrees and will end at 270 degrees. 
</para>

<para>
The ellipse will be tangent to the current position and direction of the turtle, for instance:
if <parameter>startangle</parameter> is 0 the inline axis will be perpendicular to the turtle's direction;
if <parameter>startangle</parameter> is 90 the inline axis will be parallel to the turtle's direction.
</para>

<para>
Normally, the turtle moves forward in a clockwise direction, but if the <parameter>angle</parameter> input is negative, then the turtle will move backward in a counter-clockwise direction.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Important</term>
<listitem>
<para>
FMSLogo computes the angles for the elliptic arc as if the arc had been traced on a circle and then stretched to fit on the
ellipse's axes. This means that if you choose an angle that is not zero or a multiple of 90 degrees then the actual angle (from 
the beginning of the arc to the center of the ellipse) will be either smaller or larger when compared to the
ellipse's axes in the final drawing; this will depend on the direction and amount of the ellipse's stretching.
The same applies for the angle to the end of the elliptic arc.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>Example</term>
<listitem>

<programlisting><userinput>; a 2D example
ELLIPSEARC2 90 100 200 0
ELLIPSEARC2 90  50 100 0</userinput>
</programlisting>

<programlisting><userinput>; a 2D ellipse built out of multiple consecutive arcs
SETPENSIZE 10
SETPENCOLOR "RED
ELLIPSEARC2 90 150 100 0
SETPENCOLOR "LIME
ELLIPSEARC2 90 150 100 90
SETPENCOLOR "BLUE
ELLIPSEARC2 90 150 100 180
SETPENCOLOR "YELLOW
ELLIPSEARC2 90 150 100 270</userinput>
</programlisting>

<programlisting><userinput>; a 3D example
PERSPECTIVE
REPEAT 72 [ELLIPSEARC2 90 50 100 0 RIGHTROLL 5]</userinput>
</programlisting>

</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term>See Also</term>
<listitem><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="command-ellipsearc">ELLIPSEARC</link></member>
</simplelist></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</section>
